Okay, we have one more special guest for
you and uh over the next 20 minutes or
so now. Um we have Ryan Carson. Ryan's
going to talk uh really about to
framework or not to framework. That's
the question. And I feel like over the
years we've we've very much learned not
to continually reinvent the wheel and
not to roll our own because we can build
on top of a lot of open source, a lot of
things that people have already built
and it gets us there faster. But in the
world of AI, what does that mean? Well,
to answer these questions or maybe give
us more questions to answer ourselves,
uh please welcome uh Ryan Carson who is
a serial entrepreneur, a serial founder
and seller of companies and an
incredibly smart person and also the
tallest person I think that we've had at
the conference. So that's that's really
great for me to to invite you on stage
as the final guest, Ryan. Appreciate it.
Thank you. [applause]
Hey everybody.
Lovely to see you all um in this
beautiful venue tonight. So, first of
all, I want to get to know a little bit
about you before I start. So, raise your
hand if you write code every day.
Okay, most of you. Great. Um raise your
hand again if you are a founder, were a
founder, or want to be a founder.
Cool. A lot of you. Great. Okay, so
we're going to do a visualization first.
And this is going to feel weird. Um but
trust me, it's worth it. So, we're all
going to close our eyes in a minute when
I tell you and I'm going to ask you to
visualize something. It's probably going
to take us two or three minutes to walk
through the visualization and then we're
going to talk a little bit about it. All
right. So, close your eyes. And it's
going to be weird if you don't close
your eyes because everyone else is going
to have their eyes closed. Okay. So,
close your eyes and just relax for a
second. Everyone everyone's eyes are
closed now. Great. Okay. So, imagine the
largest warehouse that you've ever seen.
It's football fields large. It's the
mass. It's it's huge. Okay. Now, inside
is completely dark and it's empty.
So, you're inside. Walk inside this
warehouse. It's completely silent.
There's no one there.
And it's dark. Okay. So, now you're
inside this huge warehouse. It's
completely black. You can't see
anything.
And then you start to see what look like
white glowing cubes that are the size of
a small room each. You start to see
thousands of them light up. They are
completely cubes. They're white. They're
glowing.
And they there are tubes connecting
each cube to other cubes. It looks like
a messy network of tubes. If you ever
been to a bank uh and you've driven
through and you put your money into a
little tube and it gets sucked up into
the bank, that's what those are.
All right, so start to walk up to the
first cube that is closest to you.
Again, it's completely silent. There's
no humans. There's thousands of these
white cube rooms that are glowing, but
you don't know what's inside. There's
tubes connecting them. They're messy.
They go everywhere.
And so you walk through the wall.
You're able to do that because we're
visualizing this. So you walk through
the wall of this cube and inside is a
ghost.
So that ghost, imagine what you want
that ghost to look like. I'll leave it
up to you.
Okay. That ghost doesn't speak. It
doesn't know you're there. And what
happens is suddenly a tube appears
in the wall from one of the uh a capsule
appears from one of these tubes and the
ghost goes over and picks it up and
looks at it.
Now the ghost has no ability to hear or
see. All it can do is read. So it picks
up this piece of paper out of this tube
and reads it.
And in on that piece of paper is all of
its knowledge that was given to it on
the paper. Now, the interesting thing
about this ghost is that it has all of
the world's information in its brain,
but it doesn't know anything beyond
that. So, it reads this piece of paper.
On that piece of paper are instructions,
uh, a list of of special tools it can
use.
And then what it does is it reads that,
decides what to do. It writes down
something on a piece of paper. It goes
to another hole in the wall, puts in the
piece of paper into a capsule, and sends
it out.
Now, there are thousands of these cubes,
and there are thousands of tubes
connecting them. There are thousands of
capsules going between all these rooms.
And this is what you need to build. So,
open your eyes.
I wanted you to visualize what it is
you're actually going to do after this
talk. So, you're no longer an engineer.
You're no longer a product manager.
You're no longer a founder. You are
someone who's going to go and fill a
warehouse
with white cubes with ghosts in them,
and you're going to try to figure out
how to connect the tubes and build
something amazing. This is the world we
live in now, right?
So I've been I got a computer science
degree 25 years ago. I was a PHP web
developer. I'm ashamed to say first. Uh
and then I started companies and built
and sold three companies. But the thing
I was most passionate about was teaching
people how to code. So for 10 years I
ran Treehouse. We taught million people
how to code. And [snorts]
all that's over
right now. You simply need to decide
which ghosts you put in the cube, what
instructions you send in, and you need
to build the tubes to other other cubes.
So, Andre Carpathy talked about agents
being ghosts, right? I thought that was
a good analogy. Uh they're not humans,
they're not computers,
they are these ethereal beings that you
can summon in about 400 milliseconds to
start to get tokens back. Um, so
currently there's about $32 trillion
of salary wages that are paid per year
to folks doing information work.
Probably we're all in that bucket,
right? What's going to happen very very
quickly is that you all are going to
start building ghosts in cubes and
connecting them via tubes to replace
that work. Um now
what will happen is that everyone that
was you know doing that information work
will get disrupted and and will either
become a a ghost master um or we'll find
other work but it's going to be
extremely disruptive. Right. I'm I'm I
think I'm older than Chris. Like I I'm
I'm old enough to have seen several of
these things happen. And as we all know
this is bigger than all of that. So the
reason why I I I title my talk uh to
framework or not to framework that is a
question is because this is all about
speed now right. So all of us who put
our hands on our keyboards every day and
ship code like to build from scratch.
You know we want to build you know the
exact TypeScript code that defines our
agent with its tools with its in with
its system prompts. uh we want to build
observability into this so we can see
traces uh you know we want to build
evals
um we want to do all this stuff and we
want to write it from from scratch but I
think we're in an age now where that is
going to slow you down and you you have
to accept that you need to start
building on top of frameworks like I'm
not paid by Mastra I'm not investing in
Mastra um but I just migrated my entire
codebase over to Mastra because it's an
agent orchestration platform form. Why
did I do that? It's so I can move
faster, right? I don't have to build
observability and eval into it now. It's
it comes out of the box, right? The
other thing to think about is with these
frameworks is that it's becoming cheaper
to switch frameworks. So, I may not like
master. I mean, give me a month, you
know, after we see it in prod and we'll
see. But I like it so far. now to move
my entire code base. So, I'm basically
building an AI agent for divorce. Um, my
two sisters got divorced and it was
gnarly and I decided divorce was
shouldn't be as painful and as
expensive. So, that's what I'm building.
And I built it from scratch using mostly
AI SDK, TypeScript of course, and that's
fine. And then I discovered, okay,
there's these platforms that do agent
orchestration for you. And it took me
probably 3 days to migrate the code. Uh
it was I think 42 commits. It was about
40,000 lines of code. Like but I did
that in like two or three days. So we're
now in an age like Chris said where code
is cheap. Um and ideas are all that
matter. So I just want to push you like
I hope you walk away from this and and
think about white cubes in a warehouse
with ghosts inside. And your job is no
longer to code. Your job is to figure
out which tubes do you connect, which
ghosts do you put in the box. Uh, and
how do you measure what is happening and
what is working? But even more
important, if you take a step back from
that, what is the information work that
you are disrupting?
Every single piece of information work
right now is going to be done by a
ghost. It will happen.
Now you can orchestrate thousands of
ghosts and hundreds of tubes, right? Uh
and this is where we're going. Um and I
would encourage you to build on top of
frameworks just because uh it's always
tempting to build it yourself and you
know feel good about I I I wrote all the
code by you know I understand exactly
what's happening but that's not where we
need to be. If you want to survive and
win uh in this bonkers new world that we
live in, you need to ship within days,
right? Not weeks, not months. Um you've
got to be fast. But the more important
thing is pick a piece of information
work that you understand and that you
care about,
build on top of a framework, get it
live, and see if anybody wants to buy
it. So short and sweet. Um, I knew it
was the end of the day, so I didn't want
to uh take a long time or or um uh talk
too long, but I just want to encourage
you to uh walk away. Think about which
piece of information work you're going
to disrupt. Think about which ghosts you
need, how many boxes you need, which
tubes are going to connect them. Um, and
then get it all wired up and out in the
world as fast as you can. Um, I I love
developers. I love building things. Um,
if you ever want to talk about it, I'm
on X. Just uh you can find me at Ryan
Carson. Um, we also have a free group
called Build Crew. If you ever want to
find a bunch of other people that are
building stuff, um, just go to
buildcrew.team and join. Um, it's free.
Uh, and that's it. So, wanted uh to keep
it short and sweet. Um, send you off
into the ether thinking about ghosts and
boxes. Um, encourage you to use
frameworks to move fast. Um, and uh, get
your idea out into the world. And that
is it.
[music]